In this video, we'll be making a low poly animal.
You can apply this technique to almost any animal,
and I've got pre-lined up reference sheets
that you can download for free.
Now this is a beginner tutorial,
but if it's a bit too fast, then do check out
my complete beginner's guide.
I won't be covering the advanced techniques,
like rigging and posing,
which you can see here,
but I do have a video about that
in my members' area.
Alternatively, you could grab
the fully-rigged animal
from my winter asset pack giveaway.
That's coming soon, so look out for that.
If you do like my content,
then check out the links in the description
to my other playlists
and my methodical and popular courses,
particularly the low poly character course,
where we do these same techniques
but in more detail.
So let's get started making our low poly animal.
So I'm in a new start-up file just here.
I've got my screencast keys down the bottom right here,
so you can see what I'm pressing.
And just as a quick reminder,
middle mouse button will move
or rotate around the middle point here,
use the wheel of your mouse to zoom in and out,
and Shift + middle mouse button will strafe around.
So let's start by bringing in my reference images.
I've drawn out a simple stag just here,
and you can download this image from my Gumroad,
link in the description,
or you can find any image of an animal,
ideally the side view is the one that's the most important,
as that's the image we trace around,
and you can kind of get away without the front view.
Alternatively, you can take a screenshot of my screen now,
if you don't want to go through the effort of downloading it.
Once you've got the file in your file browser,
you can click and drag that into Blender, like so.
And I'll minimize my file browser,
and you can see it just there.
It comes in perpendicular to your camera,
so you just need to press Alt + G,
and that removes any grabbing or movement,
and Alt + R to remove any rotation.
So we've got it right in the middle of our scene there.
I'll press R X 90 to rotate around the X-axis 90 degrees,
and press Enter.
Do remember you've got your Cartesian coordinates up here
if you're confused about which axis is which.
And now we're in the right position for front view, just here,
and I want front view looking down the Y-axis like this,
that's what we generally call front view.
And you can see that in the Cartesian coordinates here,
we want to look at the positive Y going away from us.
So that's front view just there.
Now I need to position it.
I can press 1 on my keyboard or press on the
-Y axis here to go to front view,
and now I can press G to grab to move that into position.
Although it's tricky for me to see through my cube,
so I'll just go to X-ray mode up the top here,
shortcut key is Alt + Z,
and I can now see through my objects.
And if I zoom in a bit,
you can see that I can't see the grid behind my reference image.
To solve that problem, we can go down to the
Object Data Properties.
Do make sure you've got your reference selected,
Object Data Properties,
turn Opacity on, and I'll turn this down to 0.2,
so we can nice and easily see the grid just there.
I'll press G to grab and move that above the floor.
And I want the middle of my stag to be right in the center.
Center of my scene is indicated by the 3D Cursor there.
If for any reason you've moved that,
so Shift + right click will move your 3D Cursor,
press Shift + S and go to Cursor to World Origin
to move it back into the center like that.
And now I might need to zoom in a little bit, and press G to grab
in the X-axis to move that across slightly,
and I'll hold down Shift for smaller increments,
and I can find the center somewhere around there.
And I'm looking at the face.
It's a little bit off around the legs,
but the face is probably going to be more important.
Okay, so middle mouse button to come out of front view,
and I've got my reference image set up there.
I'll press G then Y to move it backwards,
so I'm modeling in front where the cube is just here.
So you might want to pause the video, catch up with me,
bringing in your reference and placing the front view
so it's facing forward in our scene.
Pause the video and catch up.
Okay, so I need to duplicate this
and bring it to the side over here,
so I've got my side view.
So I'll go to top view for this with 7 on my numpad,
remember you can click on the Z-axis up here,
and I'll press Shift + D to duplicate and move that over to the side here.
So I've now got two reference images,
I just need to rotate this around the Z-axis,
and it should be 90 degrees, so R Z 90,
and it's gone counter-clockwise,
and it's in the right position now,
so facing forward like our reference here.
And I'll go to side view now with 3 on my numpad,
or click on the X-axis just here,
and I can now line this up.
It doesn't really matter too much where you have this,
but just make sure you press G then Y so it stays
the same height as the other one,
then they'll line up with each other,
and I just want it in front of the cube, like so.
So you've got your two reference images like this,
and we're ready to start modeling in front.
What I will do though is just bring down the Outliner,
and show you that you've got these two references just here.
I can name these by double-clicking on them, this one is "Front",
and the other one is called "Side",
nice and simple.
Now with both of them selected,
and I can select them both in the scene by Shift + left clicking,
and I've got both of them selected there,
I can move them to a new collection,
so M to move to New Collection,
and I'll call these "Reference", or "Ref" for short,
and create.
That way, it's nice and easy,
I bring down the Outliner again,
I can easily hide them and show them again,
or I can hide one or the other with the eye just there.
Okay, you might want to pause the video and catch up with me,
copying the side view and placing that in position,
and putting them both into a collection called References.
Pause the video and catch up.
Okay, so now we're ready for modeling.
So I can click on my cube,
go to side view, so I'm going to model
from side view and trace around the deer, just here.
So side view again, you can click on the X-axis here,
or numpad 3, and I'm in side view.
And I press G to grab and move that upwards into position,
and S to scale to scale it down.
So I'm roughly around this sort of chest area, just here.
Now in order to edit the cube, I want to be in Edit Mode,
so I need to go to the mode up here, the Object Mode,
and change that to Edit Mode.
And you'll see I can now edit the vertices,
edges, or faces, just there,
and that's 1, 2, and 3 on your keyboard,
not your numpad this time.
To start off with, I'm going to start with vertices,
so I can press 1,
and I can now select my different vertices.
However, if I go to side view now,
press 3 on my numpad to go to side view,
and left click on this vertex here,
notice it's actually clicked just the front one
and not the back one.
That's why it's important, if I go back to front view,
to box select like this.
And if I box select, that selects the one behind
as well, as long as you are
in X-ray mode or Wireframe mode,
he's very similar.
But we'll stay in X-ray mode for now.
Back to side view, box select both those two,
I'll zoom in a bit, I'll press G to grab
and move that up so it's in line with the top there,
then box select the bottom, move that up,
and move that so it's kind of in line along there.
These ones here, again, box select,
always make sure you're box selecting, G to grab,
to move it into position and move it
to the front of the leg there.
This one, G to grab,
and into this position here.
Okay, so I'm ready to add some more
topology or faces to my shape here.
So I need to extrude this area outwards.
In order to do that, I need to go to Face Mode up here
and select the end face here.
Again, box selecting is the easiest way to do that,
as it's sometimes a bit tricky to get them exactly.
But I've got my end face here, I can now press E to extrude,
and that brings out a new face like this.
And then I can bring it out this way, R to rotate,
and then I need to move the top and bottom vertices.
So, 1 to go to Vertex Mode,
select the bottom vertices with box select, G to grab,
move those into position, top ones here,
again, always box select,
so you're selecting the background one as well,
and I'm moving it into position.
Now you might have said, "Well, why don't you with all of them
selected, just scale them down?"
Well, that will actually scale them inwards as well,
and we don't want to do that just yet.
So you have to watch out for that, we're trying to keep this flat.
So back to side view, and I want to extrude these out to the end.
Now in terms of the distance, if I select these
endpoints here, and then go to Face Mode,
that will select the end face,
I can press E to extrude and bring that out.
Now in terms of distance, how many times you extrude out,
try and follow along with me in terms of the distance I'm covering,
and we tend to have a fairly big distance to start off with,
and then we add vertices as we need them later on,
and I'll take you through that process.
For now, let's press G to grab and bring that back
to where the leg starts, there,
rotate that slightly and move it into position,
and I've managed to get them in both the same place,
E to extrude, so we'll have one out here
in the middle of the leg,
back to Vertex Mode with 1, box select,
G to grab and move that into position,
and then again, last one, E to extrude out to here,
and I'll box select these ones,
move those into position, roughly at the top of the tail just there.
Okay, so that's extruding out to the back,
and I'll do the front as well,
so I'll select these, E to extrude, bring those out,
G to grab, and I'll rotate them slightly,
and then start moving them in, so it kind of curves up to the head,
back to Face Mode with 3, so again, you can choose Face Mode
or Vertex Mode up here if you can't remember the shortcuts,
E to extrude, bring that up, move that into position,
Vertex Mode with 1, box select, G to grab.
Now I've got a big gap here, so I'm probably going to need another
loop cut in here eventually, but I'll talk about that in just a moment.
And then back to Face Mode, select this face, E to extrude,
we might want a little bit more topology around the head,
so by topology, I mean more faces,
so I'll rotate that round, G to grab,
and then into Vertex Mode and select those,
like so. They're quite close together here,
so again, we'll need some more topology in there in a moment,
back to Face Mode, select this face, E to extrude out,
G to grab, and again, 1 to go to Vertex Mode,
and move that into position. Last one,
E to extrude out, and we'll move those into position.
So something like there is absolutely fine,
getting the basic shape to start off with,
and we're only doing the body at the moment,
we'll do the legs later on, and you'll see why
as we go through. So you might want to pause the video, catch up with me,
creating the body of the stag.
Okay, so what have we got so far?
If I move around my object, you can see
we've got this strange body of the stag,
and it's a good starting point.
If I go back to side view, notice how I have two faces
for the leg down here, that's quite handy,
because I can create a nice round shape for the legs.
So I want another loop cut going in here,
and by loop cut, I mean these edges that loop around,
like so. So if I go into perspective view,
like this, I can add in a loop cut by pressing Ctrl + R,
and that gives me this yellow loop that goes around my object.
I can then choose where I want that loop to go,
and I want it in the middle of the leg, just here,
so left click to set that, it asks you where you want it
within that area, and you can just actually right click
at this point to keep it in the center.
So that kind of cancels any of that movement.
Okay, back to side view with 3, and I've now got that in position.
I might just box select these, and move them very slightly,
so we've got more of a curve there,
and this one down very slightly,
and this one towards the front of the leg.
So we can bring out the leg from there,
and bring out the leg from here.
I did say we want a loop cut across here again,
I can press Ctrl + R from side view and do that there.
Again, I can move my mouse around to say where I want it,
left click once to set where the loop cut goes,
and then right click to cancel any movement,
and I can then box select and move these into position slightly.
Last one, we want an extra one around the head here,
so Ctrl + R to do a loop cut around there.
Double left click does the same thing,
so left click to set where I want the loop cut,
and then left click again to set the position.
And I can box select these ones up here and bring them up to there,
and these ones down here, I'll just bring those up slightly
into position.
So that's great, and we've got our base of the model.
So you might want to pause the video there, catch up with me,
making sure you've got the outline of the body shape and the head, just there.
So the next thing we want to do is cut our shape in half,
so we only need to work on one side,
and use a Mirror Modifier to copy that side
to the other side.
So in order to cut the shape in half,
we need a loop cut going down the middle.
So I'll press Ctrl + R, and there's my loop cut
going down the middle.
I'll just come round to here so you can see it more easily,
Ctrl + R, loop cut down the middle,
left click once to say where you want the loop cut,
and then again, left click to set the position.
Let me accidentally move it slightly and left click just there,
it's slightly off center and that's not going
to work for us in this particular situation.
So you can either undo that and try it again,
or you can come down to the dialog box here,
and the Factor, just there, you can see it should be
at zero, so I'll select that,
change it to zero, and it's right down the center now.
So now I want to delete half my shape.
So I can go up to the top here, select Faces,
and box select all the faces at the back here,
as you can see there.
And then press Delete, and then Faces.
So that deletes all my faces, and I've got
half my shape there.
So now I can add my Mirror Modifier to create the other half.
So we go to the Modifiers just here,
so the spanner, or the wrench if you're American,
Add Modifier, and then just start typing in "Mirror",
and it will search for Mirror just there,
it's under the Generate.
So I'll click on the Mirror just there, and you can see
it's created the other half.
We're still in X-ray view, I can press Alt + Z
so you can see that more easily,
and that's looking nice.
Now, the Mirror Modifier, you can see over here,
it defaults to the X-axis.
That's why we often model with the X-axis
going across, because lots of the modifiers
will default to X like this.
We can also, to help us, turn on Clipping, just here,
to make sure it sticks together in the middle.
If I keep that unticked for the moment,
and go to Vertex Mode, select this vertex here and press G to grab,
you can split it apart like that.
I'll undo that, and I'll turn Clipping on,
and press G to grab, and now I can't move it,
I can only move it in the Y and Z axes,
not the X-axis.
So that's very helpful.
So now what we need to do is create some legs
that can come down from the body.
Now you might be thinking, I can select the faces
at the bottom, so go to Face Mode with 3,
select these faces just here,
and then E to extrude and bring them down.
But obviously, the faces are joined together
in the middle, so that's not working.
What I need to do instead is undo that,
and create another loop cut going around the middle here,
and then I can bring the faces down.
Before we do that though, it might be a good idea to
select all these faces at the very end here,
let's actually go to X-ray mode for that, it's much easier,
again, select all those faces there,
that will select the outside faces,
go to front view with 1, or again, click the Cartesian coordinates,
just make sure I'm lined up with the edge
of the body just there, so G then X,
move that out so I've got the furthest point just there,
and then I can start bringing all these in, in a moment.
So I need a loop cut going down the middle here,
so I can extrude some faces on the outside.
I'll show you what that looks like, so Ctrl + R to do a loop cut,
left click to set the position, right click to cancel any movement,
and you can see the Factor is zero there.
I'll just minimize this dialog box, it's in the way.
And now I can go to Face Mode with 3,
I'll just turn off X-ray views,
so we can see that a bit more easily,
select these faces just here, you might want to go to
side view, just to make sure you've got the correct faces
lining up with your leg.
I'm just showing you what it looks like from this position,
and I can press E to extrude to bring that down,
and that's creating some legs now.
Let's go to side view so we can start lining those up.
I can actually press S to scale now,
to bring them in a little bit, and you can see
they're coming in slightly there, back to side view,
and then I can extrude these out.
I'll go back to X-ray view, so I can see the shape more easily,
into Vertex Mode, and I can box select the vertices,
and move them into position.
And then again, back to Face Mode to select them all
and extrude them out.
And I can rotate them round, E to extrude,
scale these up very slightly,
so I'm just creating a bit of a lump for the leg,
E to extrude, scale them down,
E to extrude, scale down,
slightly in the middle somewhere around there,
and E to extrude, scale it up,
and remember R to rotate if you need to,
E to extrude, scale this up,
and rotate those around slightly,
E to extrude, scale those down,
and you can actually press here, S Z 0,
to flatten them all out.
So it's scaling in the Z-axis, which is up and down,
zero, so they're all flattened.
I can now scale it out slightly, and move that to the front, like so,
and make sure it's on the floor.
Let's see what that looks like, it's not too bad,
it's a bit wide at the moment, but we'll sort that out in a moment.
Let's do the same for the back,
you might want to challenge yourself to extrude out the back leg.
So first catch up with me, creating the front leg,
and then have a go at doing the back leg for yourself.
Pause the video and have a go at that.
Okay, so I'll select these two faces here,
I'll go to side view now, 3 on my numpad,
E to extrude, bring that down, and scale it in,
and move it backwards slightly.
I can scale in the Y as well, to constrain
that scaling to the Y-axis, and bring that in,
so it doesn't go too thin, probably about right,
and again, back to side view, and extrude out.
I'll go back to X-ray view, so I can see the shape more easily,
into Vertex Mode, and I can box select the vertices,
and move them into position, and then again,
back to Face Mode to select them all and extrude them out.
And I'll speed this footage up now.
So I've got this basic shape here,
and it's turning out relatively good.
Now it's a case of adding a bit more shape to the body.
So I'll turn off X-ray mode with Alt + Z,
and I need some topology in the middle here,
so I can start bringing the top edges
and the bottom edges in, so I can get that curve.
So Ctrl + R to do a loop cut across the middle,
and we'll start off with just one, left click,
and left click again to set the position,
or right click to cancel.
And now I can start thinking about moving my faces into position.
We'll start off with the legs, and we'll get them in a relatively similar position.
So from front view, Alt + Z to get to X-ray mode,
select all the legs here, G to grab
in the X-axis, and bring those in, somewhere around there.
Now the back legs might be a little bit wider, so I can
deselect some faces by Ctrl + box selecting
some faces like this. Oh, I'm in Edge Mode, not Face Mode,
it doesn't matter too much, but I'll go back to Face Mode,
so it only selects those faces, and I need to bring those out slightly,
so G then X to bring them out.
I'll go to front view so you can see how far out I'm going.
I didn't draw these in in my reference,
but probably somewhere around here for the back legs there.
That looks good.
The whole face we want to bring in,
the face and the neck, and we can see from this point here
in my reference image, so this point just here,
which is up to I think roughly around there,
don't panic if you don't get it perfect,
I'll just Ctrl + box select these,
go to front view, so about right, and G then X
to bring those in. Now just be careful here,
I'm going fairly close to the middle,
I don't want this line to touch the middle.
If I do that, I'll press G then X, don't follow along with this,
and bring that into the middle, it's now stuck,
and we've got this strange triangle here, and we've got these extra
faces which you can actually click on in the middle here,
which are a bit of a pain, so we would have to unclip things and pull them back out,
that's a bit awkward. I'll undo that with Ctrl + Z,
and just bring them in so they're fairly close, so G then X
to the middle there, so you've got that small face in the middle,
I'll just go to front view so we can see how close we are.
And now I'll select these ones here,
let me see how far down we can go,
Ctrl + deselect these ones,
and Ctrl + deselect these ones as well,
and I want to bring these in now, so again, to front view,
G to grab, move those in, I might rotate as well,
so it slowly comes up from the bottom like that,
so I've got a slow taper in, like so,
that's not too bad.
Now we want to create a little bit of curve going across here as well,
I can select this whole edge going along here
by going to Edge Mode, and then Alt + left clicking
on the edge loop as it's known, that I want to select,
so Alt + left click to select those.
Incidentally, you can double left click if you're emulating
3-button mouse using a Mac or something like that,
and I can press GG to edge slide, so grab twice,
GG, edge slide that in,
and GG again to edge slide it back the other way,
and I'm moving my mouse to say which edge I want to slide across,
and I'm bringing that back down to somewhere around there.
And I can do the same with this one here,
the edge loop stops at poles, these are known as poles,
any vertex that hasn't got four edges going into it,
so when you select an edge loop, they stop at poles,
and now GG to slide that in, like so.
This one along here from here up to here,
so Alt + left click, GG to edge slide that in,
and we're slowly creating the shape of our animal.
So from this point on, it's a case of a little bit of sculpting,
I guess, by moving vertices around,
it does take a bit of experience to get this correct,
but that's kind of the artistic side
that will take a bit of time to learn,
but you can follow along with me.
So again, I'll press GG on this one, GG to slide it back up,
so there's a bit more of a curve going around here.
Now the face is the correct size here,
but a bit fat at the front here, so to Face Mode,
and I'll select these two faces just here and here,
G to grab in the X and bring those in.
It's not looking too bad there, that will need a bit of tidy up,
and at the back here, we'll need to curve this around,
and we can curve the legs round in the same way,
so 2 to go to Edge Mode, select that end edge,
GG to edge slide, and bring that towards the back,
I don't need to slide it forwards, just towards
the middle of my creature, the same with these,
here, GG, slide those in,
towards the middle, this one here, GG,
slide away from the middle there,
and it creates some curve to the leg, and this one here,
GG, sliding back out,
so we've got some rounded legs there,
that's why I had this extra loop cut
going through the middle here, so we could create some curve,
otherwise you come out with very square legs.
And remember we started with two faces just here at the bottom,
and we did the same for the front, so I'll do exactly the same there,
so GG, with that edge loop selected,
select this edge loop, GG, bring that in,
and this one here, GG to edge slide,
and this one here, GG to edge slide.
And now we're starting to get the shape a bit more.
Probably need a bit more rounded shape
from the top from here down to here,
so I'll GG to slide that in,
it's very flat-bummed, so I'm going to select
this just single vertex here, and slide that in,
and I'll slide these along so it's a bit more even,
these two here, I'll just grab them, move them forward,
and that's looking about right. And this one in here,
G to grab in the Z, and bring that up,
so the legs come up into the middle there,
probably about right, and we're looking good.
So I'll just come out of X-ray mode and show you what we've got,
got quite a nice looking animal just there.
And now we need to add the detail on the head.
So let's zoom into the head a bit,
I think an extra loop cut across here will help us out,
so Ctrl + R, loop cut across there, let's go to side view,
and just marry that up a bit with the reference image,
so again, X-ray view, and move these in slightly,
move these ones across, and these ones
I can move around the eye, to give me some detail,
so I can bring out the eye from there, and let's bring these in,
just moving some of these vertices around.
If your camera goes into a weird position, press period key,
and it zooms in on the object,
let's take a quick look at the reference in front view.
It can be quite tricky to line up your vertices,
so you might just need to move out of front view slightly,
look around a bit, again, press period key on your numpad
to zoom in and frame selected, you can find that under the View menu there,
Frame Selected, and then I can bring these in,
so G then X, bring those in,
and let me just look at front view again,
this is the muzzle just here, bring those in, that looks good,
this is the cheek just here by the looks of things,
so I've just got to think how wide I want that to be,
it might be about right, possibly a little bit wider,
so let's just go back to front view, yeah, looks a little bit wide there,
this needs to come up actually, so I might need to do
some extra topology for the eyes, as I was talking about earlier,
oh, and the horns need to come out of here, don't they, so I do need to come up a bit,
horns from here, and the ears from here, so we're going to need a little bit more
movement there, coming outwards,
but the rest looks okay. And again, you'll need to move around a fair bit,
I'm reasonably experienced when it comes to understanding
what vertices and so forth I'm selecting,
so you might need to do a little bit of moving around
more than I am here, but I think I'm roughly there with the shape.
Oh, and these faces here need to come in a bit,
so I've drawn that line there, that's the front shoulder,
I guess, so I can bring these in, G to grab,
bring those in, somewhere around there, that looks good,
and these ones here, I think they need to go in,
so not those ones though, G then X, remember to Ctrl + box select
to deselect objects, and that's looking relatively good,
maybe a little bit more of a chest though, G then X, bring those out,
and I'll bring those in, just so it's even.
We're roughly getting there, I would say.
I might want to even these out a little bit, so GG to edge slide,
to create some sort of smoothness between them,
and can you see how evening those out made it a bit smoother
around there. If you're following along with me, then you might want to pause the video here,
and just catch up, and do save your work at this point.
Okay, so let's think about the eye,
so let me go to side view, and in order to do the eye,
it's a bit tricky, this one, so in Face Mode,
select the face there, and I I to inset
and bring a face out like so,
and I can start moving these a bit closer
into position, and then I can move those
to the front there, scale those down, move that to the back,
and I might have an eye just there,
it's not too bad, it looks a little bit like it's coming inwards,
and it probably needs to come outwards, so I'll go to front view,
see where the eye position is there, it's slightly misaligned
on my reference, that's a bad drawing from me,
so let's just get that face just there,
back to front view, and I probably want that to come out like so,
and then rotate around the Z-axis, so it's slightly looking forward,
mainly to the side, but I'll scale that up,
rotate it just there, so it's looking forward a bit,
but mainly to the side, like so.
So we got a simple eye just there, and I'll just even this out,
so GG to edge slide that along.
Back to side view, and think about the ear, I think we can come out from
this face here, we might need an extra loop cut around here,
so let me do one more, so Ctrl + R to bring a loop cut along there,
select this one, and slide it along a bit, so GG,
I can use this, in fact, to help me just here,
in fact, an extra one in here would make sense, wouldn't it?
So Ctrl + R to do a loop cut, so I can just create a little bit more
shape in these areas, like so,
and I can smooth out at the top here if I want to,
I think actually I need to select from here to here,
I can Ctrl + left click to take the shortest path
between two points, and select everything in between,
and just slide those, GG, and slide them forward or back,
and these ones, probably up to here, GG to slide those down and back,
create a bit more roundness to the body,
and now I'm ready for the ear, just about anyway,
so probably need to come out somewhere around here, don't we?
Might need to move these ones up a little bit, that area there,
so let's just choose that face, so that one just there,
looks a bit high, let me look from front view as well,
yeah, let's bring that out slightly, rotate it around,
so you rotate perpendicular to the camera,
I might inset it first, so I to inset,
so I've got a new face there that I can come out from,
and then I can just sort of bring that out really slightly,
and then E to extrude for the ear, like so,
and then E to extrude again, scale that down,
we've got a very basic ear there, I'll just bring this up,
so it looks more ear shaped, like this,
and I might have to just even my topology out a little bit,
so very, very basic ear there, actually it looks like they face
forward more, doesn't it, on a little bit skewed with mine,
so again, select those faces there,
and rotate them round, again, you rotate perpendicular to the camera,
it's going to be a bit careful with this, can you see how
this particular face here is really, really skewed,
so I just need to bring this back to level and even it out slightly,
and we're going to need some space for the horns as well,
which is going to be interesting, so we're going to have to
create some space in here, and come out from this area, probably,
let's select that face, and then go to front view,
and that actually should work for the horn, let's go to side view and see how that marries up,
maybe not back far enough, that's the problem with that one,
actually looking at some reference images, looks like the horns
are actually in front there, just above the eyes,
in front of the ears, so actually this is great,
it's working out nicely, so I'll inset here,
and then bring out the horns, I'll inset with I, that is,
and then G to grab, lifting it up really slightly,
and then E to extrude outwards, bring that in,
ready for a horn to come out.
This is a tough one as well, the horns,
but if you E to extrude, you can come outwards slightly,
and then if you want a different direction,
so let's say you want to come out from here, E to extrude,
and scale down, and you can bring them out like so,
I'll just turn off X-ray, so you can kind of see what's going on here,
so I can scale that down, G to grab, move it up,
and then come back to this one here to extrude out further,
E to extrude, move that backwards this time, and rotate that around,
and that can come out this way, so E to extrude again,
scale down, try not to go too far, otherwise it inverts itself,
so scale that down like so, and then just rotate it round into different positions,
and I can press E to extrude a little bit, and then I can come out
from a different angle, so E to extrude and bring that out like so,
and then back to this one, E to extrude, scale down, and so forth,
so you can see how slowly I'm making some horns here.
Now remember, you can go to X-ray mode, select all,
and you can just scale them up very slightly,
if they're going a bit too thin, for example,
or you can select edge loops by going to Edge Mode,
select an edge loop, try and get the edge loop there, with Alt + left click,
and scale them up that way as well.
So back to Face Mode, and I'll extrude this out,
in fact, I'll just grab it up to here, extrude it out a little bit further,
and this one can come into the front here, so E to extrude,
and I'll just do a little bit of rotation here,
so come to the top view, remember you're rotating perpendicular to your camera,
this might need a fair bit of adaptation,
the horns are probably the hardest bit, I would say.
If you need to do any extra loop cuts, remember Ctrl + R,
you can use the wheel of your mouse as well, if you want to create a couple of loop cuts,
and then position those, and I can create a bit more of a curve
coming around like that.
And if you want another horn coming out from a certain area, then loop cut,
Face Mode, I'll just go back out of X-ray mode,
so you can see that more easily, E to extrude, and bring it out from these areas.
Might need a little bit more weight at the front here, so I'll just bring that back,
and you can just adjust your vertices slightly,
if you need to, a little bit oblong shape, so I'll bring those in.
These ones as well, just be careful not to box select
and select something behind, that can be really awkward.
Remember also if you're trying to select vertices in the background,
go to X-ray mode before doing that.
And let's see how we're getting on.
That's not too bad at the moment.
Needs a bit of adjustment and rounding out,
particularly the front here, you can select a vertex
and Ctrl + select another vertex that's further down,
and it takes the shortest path, so Ctrl + left click,
so if I Ctrl + left click here, it'll take the shortest path,
and I can GG to slide that back,
probably bring these forward, and this one back a bit more,
and this one back a bit more, looks quite wide-mouthed, doesn't it?
I'm going to bring these in a bit, in fact, from here to here,
no, from here to here, GG, bring those back in.
Go to front view, X-ray mode, to just have a quick look at my references,
yeah, I feel like these need to come in a bit,
just make sure you don't select anything in the back there,
and bring those in.
I think we're slowly getting there, I would say.
I might want to even these out a little bit, so GG to edge slide,
to create some sort of smoothness between them,
and can you see how evening those out made it a bit smoother around there.
If you're following along with me, then you might want to pause the video here,
and just catch up, and do save your work at this point.
Okay, so let me think about the tail then for the modeling,
so I'll come to the back here, 3 to get Face Mode,
select this end face here, and I'll inset it,
so I to inset, if you press B for boundary,
that will turn off the boundary that is
the mirror just here, so we can make sure it's linked together
with the other side, bring that up, and then
I'll scale it down a bit more, and then E to extrude,
and then just tidy up a little bit here, so smooth it out a bit,
and then select the end, Face Mode, and extrude that out,
let's go to side view so I can see it,
and we got a really basic tail just there.
Again, a bit of smoothing, just by edge sliding,
you can smooth these things out, as you can see there.
So GG for edge slide.
Okay, so we've got the basic model there,
I'll do a little bit of tidying up, and I'll speed up the footage,
I'll just sort the antlers out a little bit.
The antlers on my reference are much bigger,
so I might make them a bit bigger in fact.
Every now and again, you might want to go back to solid mode as well,
just to see how the shape's looking, and I think that's looking
relatively good, just going to curve these out a little bit more.
And again, to smooth areas out, GG to edge slide
them along, and that generally smoothes them out quite well.
Period key to zoom in on a certain area, so if course,
you might want to pause the video here, catch up with me,
making sure that you've got the right outline of your shape,
and then we'll move together to the shading.
Although my final render was black and white,
you might want to do some shading, so let's go to the Shading workspace,
so I can show you how to add colors to your stag.
So, in order to do the shading, we go across to the Shading workspace
at the top here, I'll zoom in on my stag,
I don't really need the references anymore, so I can again,
bring down the Outliner and hide the references there,
and I've got my stag just here.
Now to start with, we can give the stag a nice brown material,
we've got the default material here, if you can't see one,
you might see something, if I close this down, like this,
then just click on New Material, that's fine.
I'll call this "Brown", in fact, I'll call it "Light Brown",
so this can be the main color of the stag,
so I might choose a dark brown later on, and add those
perhaps to the hooves and things. Base Color just here,
I can click on that, and change it across to the brown,
so that's across to the oranges, and then bring the Value down,
and that creates brown, so a fairly orangey brown,
maybe a little bit less saturated, so in towards the middle
of the circle for less saturation, you can actually use a slider
down here as well, all the time I'm looking at this color here.
And to me, that looks roughly right.
It's very shiny, as you can see, and fur isn't particularly reflective,
so we can bring up the Roughness of that, and already
that's looking quite nice. We want a few areas though where it's darker,
as I was saying, so you might want to look at some references for this,
but the horns might be a bit more gray, so I'll zoom in on those,
go to Edit Mode, and I want to add a new color
to the horns. Now in order to do this, we need to add a new material
slot just here, so under the slots, in the drop down,
we add a new material, and you can see a new material
being created there, and we've got a button at the bottom where we can assign it
to certain faces, so I'll just select those faces that I want,
Alt + Z to go to X-ray mode, 3 to go to Face Mode,
and I'll try and select those faces, you can Ctrl + right click
to lasso select like that, and you can generally get
a better selection, and I got a bit lucky there and got them all.
So that's good, got my horns just there, and I want to
under the slots, assign those to Slot 2.
So at the moment, they go white because there is no texture
in Slot 2, so it creates a default texture,
so we need to add in Slot 2 a new material just here,
and this one I'll call "Dark Brown", and again,
I'll go across to the browns, I'll just make it slightly darker,
and you should be able to see that it's changing the horns
just there, and that's great. Let's go out of Edit Mode,
and just see what that looks like, that's looking good.
Let's create a darker material still for things like the eyes.
So again, into Edit Mode, I can select both those eyes,
create a new slot, so under my slots, New Slot,
and we got a new material slot there, we're going to assign it,
and it goes white because there's no material,
so let's add a new material, and I'll call this, in fact,
let's call it "Black", and we'll add a black color this time,
so this time, Base Color, bring it down almost to black,
I don't like to go completely black, a little bit across the browns,
and very dark just there, and we got an almost black,
and you can see that eye just there.
Remember these particular materials have a different Roughness
to the light brown, so let's go back to the dark brown just here,
and let's say I want to change the dark brown,
give that a little bit more Roughness, so it's not so shiny,
and that looks good. The eyes though, makes sense
to have them shiny, and that's looking quite good,
and that's great, I can now start adding texture to the other areas,
so at the front here, we might want it the same color as the eyes,
now, let's just quickly go to front view,
and bring back my reference, Alt + Z to get to X-ray mode.
Now I'm in X-ray mode, but you can't actually see the background,
so I will need to go to probably Wireframe mode this time,
and you can see the shape of the nose just there,
it's not the full shape that I've got it at the moment,
so we'll probably going to need to use the knife tool for this again,
so I'll go back to Solid mode with X-ray turned on,
in fact, let's turn X-ray off, and I'll just draw in
with the knife tool, so K for the knife tool,
from about here, and I'll just create the shape
down to here, I think, so press Enter,
and I've got the shape just there. Didn't go all the way to the middle there,
actually, so K for the knife tool and I can just create a cut across there,
press Enter, I can actually get rid of this edge here, so 2 to Edge Mode,
select that edge, and press Ctrl + X to dissolve.
So I've got that nose at the front there, and I actually want a mouth as well,
so I'm going to do that as well, K for knife tool,
I can come across here, and you can go through two at the same time,
like so, and back again to there, and press Enter,
so I've got a basic mouth, looks like they're smiling there, though,
so I might have to come in here, K for knife tool,
and just make it a bit more square, like that,
so it's not smiling, select this edge, Ctrl + X to dissolve it,
and we've got the basics of our mouth just there.
So I can select those faces, so Face Mode, select those faces,
I'm in Solid mode at the moment, Material Preview mode will show
my actual materials just here, and then I can give those
the Black texture just here, so Black and Assign,
out of Edit Mode so I can see the results, that looks relatively good there.
So that should give you enough idea about how to add color
or materials to your object, and assign them to different faces.
Again, if you want to learn more about how to pose the animal,
then do check out the Members' area of this channel,
and if you like this sort of content, then do check out my low poly
character course. Alternatively, there's lots of good playlists
on this channel, I would recommend the Low Poly Whale
as your next tutorial series, so why not check that out?
If you've got any questions, then do comment below.
Thanks for watching, and I'll see you next time.